Guide to the Dorothy M. Johnson-Kay Burnham Correspondence 1952-1977
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Dorothy M. Johnson-Kay Burnham Correspondence
1952-1977
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 210
Johnson, Dorothy M., 1905-1984
0.5 linear feet
Catherine (Kay) Burnham was a clinical psychologist and close friend of Montana writer Dorothy Johnson. This collection primarily consists of correspondence from Johnson to Burnham.
Biographical Note
Catherine (Kay) Burnham was a clinical psychologist and close friend of Dorothy Johnson. The two women met while living in New York City and often traveled together. Dorothy Johnson dedicated The Hanging Tree to "Kay Burnham" and, according to Burnham's brother, Catherine helped select shooting locations for the film adaptation. Catherine Burnham died of a heart attack in June 1988.
This collection primarily consists of correspondence from author Dorothy M. Johnson to Catherine Burnham from 1956 to 1977. It also includes newspaper clippings, two poems, and a travel visa.
The collection is divided into four series:
Series I: Correspondence, 6 folders, 1956-1977
Series II: Clippings, 1 folder, 1952-1969, 1 folder
Series III: Writings, 1 folder, 1974
Series IV: Personal, 1 folder, 1960
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
The materials in this collection remained with Catherine Burnham until her death, at which time her brother assumed custody of her estate. The materials remained with him until he donated the collection to the K. Ross Toole Archives six years after her death.
Gift of Mark Burnham, 1994
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Burnham, Kay--Correspondence
Montana; Literature
- Correspondence, 1956-1977; Series I; 6 folders
  This series primarily consists of correspondence from Dorothy Johnson. Folders 1-4 are a chronological series of correspondence from Dorothy Johnson to Kay Burnham. Folder 5 consists of undated correspondence. Folder 6 consists of correspondence from third parties. Notable items in this series include Dorothy Johnson's recounting of: a story of a human skull which was said to have been given to the Knights Templar and used by them in ceremony; her interaction with Hollywood figures including Gary Cooper; her adoption by the Blackfoot Tribe; and the death of her mother.
  - Correspondence, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1977 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Correspondence, (From third parties) (Box-folder 1/6)
- Clippings, 1952-1969; Series II; 1 folder
  This series consists of several newspaper clippings primarily pertaining to Dorothy Johnson.
  - Clippings, 1952-1974 (Box-folder 1/7)
- Writings, 1974; Series III; 1 folder
  This series consists of two poems, one item entitled The Lucky Lady, and an article entitled "Montana," written by Dorothy Johnson for the Encyclopedia Britannica and dated 1974.
  - Poems (Box-folder 1/8)
- Personal, 1960; Series IV; 1 folder
  This series contains Catherine Burnham's 1960 Mexican visa.
  - Visa, 1960 (Box-folder 1/9)